Everyone is both a learner
كل واحد منا متعلم
and a teacher.
ومعلم في نفس الوقت
This is me being inspired
هذا أنا يجري إلهامي
by my first tutor,
بواسطة معلمي الأول
my mom,
أمي
and this is me teaching
وهذا أنا أقوم بتدريس
Introduction to Artificial Intelligence
مقدمة الى الذكاء الاصطناعي
to 200 students
ل200 طالب
at Stanford University.
في جامعة ستانفورد
Now the students and I
والآن فإنني والطلاب
enjoyed the class,
مستمتعون بالفصل
but it occurred to me
ولكن ظهر لي
that while the subject matter
أنه وبالرغم من ان موضوع الدرس
of the class is advanced
متقدماَ
and modern,
وحديثاً
the teaching technology isn't.
إلا أن تقنية التدريس ليست كذلك
In fact, I use basically
في الواقع ، فإنني أستخدم في الأساس
the same technology as
نفس التقنية
this 14th-century classroom.
كالتي استخدمت في فصل القرن الرابع عشر
Note the textbook,
لاحظوا الكتاب المدرسي
the sage on the stage,
الحكيم على المنصة
and the sleeping guy
والرجل النائم
in the back. (Laughter)
في الخلف. (ضحك)
Just like today.
تماماً مثل اليوم
So my co-teacher,
لذلك فإن مدرسي المساعد
Sebastian Thrun, and I thought,
سيباستيان ثرون و أنا فكرنا
there must be a better way.
لابد أن يكون هناك وسيلة أفضل
We challenged ourselves
تحدينا أنفسنا
to create an online class
لابتكار فصل عبر الانترنت
that would be equal or better
بحيث يكون مساوياً أو أفضل
in quality to our Stanford class,
في الجودة لفصلنا في ستانفورد
but to bring it to anyone
ولكن لاحضاره لأي شخص
in the world for free.
في العالم مجاناً
We announced the class on July 29th,
أعلنا عن الفصل في 29 من يوليو
and within two weeks, 50,000 people
وخلال اسبوعين قام 50.000 شخص
had signed up for it.
بالاشتراك فيه
And that grew to 160,000 students
وقد نما هذا الى 160.000 طالب
from 209 countries.
من 209 دولة
We were thrilled to have
لقد غمرتنا السعادة
that kind of audience,
لحصولنا على هذا النوع من المشاهدين
and just a bit terrified that we
ولكننا ارتعبنا قليلاً
hadn't finished preparing the class yet. (Laughter)
لأننا لم ننته من تجهيز الفصل بعد . (ضحك)
So we got to work.
لذا فقد شرعنا في العمل
We studied what others had done,
درسنا ماذا فعل الآخرون
what we could copy and what we could change.
ما الذي يمكننا نسخه و ماالذي نستطيع تغييره
Benjamin Bloom had showed
لقد أظهر بينجامين بلوم
that one-on-one tutoring works best,
ان التدريس الخاص من شخص الى شخص يعمل بطريقة أفضل
so that's what we tried to emulate,
لذلك فقد حاولنا محاكاة
like with me and my mom,
مثل ما كان معي ومع أمي
even though we knew
رغم اننا علمنا
it would be one-on-thousands.
أنه سيكون من شخص الى آلاف
Here, an overhead video camera
هنا ، يوجد كاميرا فيديو فوقية
is recording me as I'm talking
تسجلني اثناء حديثي
and drawing on a piece of paper.
ورسمي على قطعة من الورق
A student said, "This class felt
قال احد الطلاب ، "أن هذا الدرس أشعرني
like sitting in a bar
انني اجلس في حانة
with a really smart friend
مع صديق ذكي بالفعل
who's explaining something
حيث يقوم بشرح شيئٍ ما
you haven't grasped, but are about to."
لم تستطع استيعابه ، ولكنك على وشك"
And that's exactly what we were aiming for.
وهذا بالضبط ما هدفنا إليه
Now, from Khan Academy, we saw
الآن ، من أكاديمية كان ، رأينا
that short 10-minute videos
أن هذه الفيديوهات القصيرة ذات العشر دقائق
worked much better than trying
تعمل أفضل كثيراً من محاولة
to record an hour-long lecture
تسجيل محاضرة طولها ساعة
and put it on the small-format screen.
ووضعها على شاشة صغيرة
We decided to go even shorter
فقد قررنا ان تكون أقصر بكثير
and more interactive.
وتفاعلية أكثر
Our typical video is two minutes,
فيديوهاتنا في الغالب دقيقتان
sometimes shorter, never more
أحياناً أقصر ، ولكنها لا تطول
than six, and then we pause for
عن ستة ، ثم نتوقف
a quiz question, to make it
لاعطاء سؤال اختبار ، لجعلها
feel like one-on-one tutoring.
تبدو وكأنها درس من شخص لشخص
Here, I'm explaining how a computer uses
هنا ، أنا أشرح كيف يستخدم الكمبيوتر
the grammar of English
قواعد اللغة الانجليزية
to parse sentences, and here,
لتحليل الجمل ، وهنا
there's a pause and the student
يوجد توقف وعلى الطالب
has to reflect, understand what's going on
ان يعكس ، يفهم ما الذي يدور
and check the right boxes
ويختار الصندوق الصحيح
before they can continue.
وقبل ان يتسطيعون الاستمرار
Students learn best when
فقد تعلم الطلاب جيداً متى
they're actively practicing.
يتدربون بنشاط
We wanted to engage them, to have them grapple
لقد أردنا أن نشركهم ، لنجعلهم يشتبكون
with ambiguity and guide them to synthesize
مع الغموض وندلهم على توليف
the key ideas themselves.
الأفكار الرئيسية بأنفسهم
We mostly avoid questions
نحن في الغالب نتفادى الاسئلة
like, "Here's a formula, now
من قبيل ، " توجد معادلة , الآن
tell me the value of Y
اخبرني عن قيمة ص
when X is equal to two."
عندما تكون قيمة س اثنان"
We preferred open-ended questions.
لقد فضلنا الاسئلة المفتوحة
One student wrote, "Now I'm seeing
كتب أحد الطلاب " الأن أنا أرى
Bayes networks and examples of
شبكات بايز وأمثلة من
game theory everywhere I look."
نظرية اللعب في أي مكان أنظر اليه
And I like that kind of response.
وأنا أحب مثل هذا النوع من الرد
That's just what we were going for.
هذا بالضبط ما نحن مقدمون عليه
We didn't want students to memorize the formulas;
لا نريد للطلاب أن يحفظوا المعادلات
we wanted to change the way
لقد اردنا تغيير الطريقة
they looked at the world.
التي ينظرون بها إلى العالم
And we succeeded.
وقد نجحنا
Or, I should say, the students succeeded.
أو ، يجب القول ، أن الطلاب قد نجحوا
And it's a little bit ironic
وهذا ساخر قليلاً
that we set about to disrupt traditional education,
أننا قد تحلقنا حول تعطيل التعليم التقليدي
and in doing so, we ended up
ولعمل ذلك ، فقد انتهينا
making our online class
لصنع فصلنا عبر الانترنت
much more like a traditional college class
يشبه كثيراً صف الكلية التقليدي
than other online classes.
عن الفصول الأخرى عبر الانترنت
Most online classes, the videos are always available.
معظم فصول الانترنت ، تتم اتاحة الفيديوهات على الدوام
You can watch them any time you want.
يمكنك مشاهدة الفيديو في أي وقت تريد
But if you can do it any time,
ولكن إذا كنت تستطيع فعل ذلك في أي وقت
that means you can do it tomorrow,
فهذا يعني انك تستطيعه غداً
and if you can do it tomorrow,
وإذا كنت تستطيعه غداً
well, you may not ever
حسناً ، يمكنك
get around to it. (Laughter)
ألا تأتي ناحيته أبداً . (ضحك)
So we brought back the innovation
لذلك فقد استرجعنا ابتكار
of having due dates. (Laughter)
ان يكون لدينا تواريخ محددة . (ضحك)
You could watch the videos
يمكنك مشاهدة الفيديوهات
any time you wanted during the week,
في أي وقت تريد أثناء الأسبوع
but at the end of the week,
ولكن في نهاية الأسبوع
you had to get the homework done.
يجب عليك عمل الواجب المنزلي
This motivated the students to keep going, and it also
وقد دفع هذا الطلاب للمضي قدماً وكذلك
meant that everybody was working
عنى أن الجميع يعملون
on the same thing at the same time,
على نفس الموضوع في نفس الوقت
so if you went into a discussion forum,
لذلك إذا ذهبت إلى منتدى النقاش
you could get an answer from a peer within minutes.
يمكنك الحصول على الاجابة من نظير لك خلال دقائق
Now, I'll show you some of the forums, most of which
الآن ، سأريكم بعض المنتديات ، معظمها
were self-organized by the students themselves.
كانت منظمة ذاتياً بواسطة الطلاب أنفسهم
From Daphne Koller and Andrew Ng, we learned
من دافن كولار وأندرو نج ، تعلمنا
the concept of "flipping" the classroom.
مفهوم تقليب الفصول
Students watched the videos
طلاب يشاهدون الفيديوهات
on their own, and then they
بمفردهم ، ومن ثم
come together to discuss them.
يأتون معاً لمناقشته
From Eric Mazur, I learned about peer instruction,
من إيريك مازور، تعلمت عن تعليمات النظير
that peers can be the best teachers,
ان هؤلاء النظراء يمكن أن يكونوا أفضل مدرسين
because they're the ones
لأنهم هم الأشخاص
that remember what it's like to not understand.
الذين يتذكرون ما الذي لا يمكن فهمه
Sebastian and I have forgotten some of that.
أنا و سيباستيان نسينا بعض هذا
Of course, we couldn't have
بالطبع ، لم يكن لدينا
a classroom discussion with
فصل مناقشة
tens of thousands of students,
فيه عشرات الآلاف من الطلاب
so we encouraged and nurtured these online forums.
لذلك فقد شجعنا و رعينا هذه المنتديات عبر الانترنت
And finally, from Teach For America,
وفي النهاية ، من التعليم لأمريكا
I learned that a class is not
فقد تعلمت أن الفصل الدراسي
primarily about information.
لايكون في الأساس عن المعلومات
More important is motivation and determination.
والأهم هو الابتكار و التصميم
It was crucial that the students see
لقد كان حاسماً أن يرى الطلاب
that we're working hard for them and
أننا نعمل بجد من أجلهم و
they're all supporting each other.
أنهم يقومون بدعم بعضهم البعض
Now, the class ran 10 weeks,
الآن ، عمل الفصل الدراسي 10 أسابيع
and in the end, about half of the 160,000 students watched
وفي النهاية ، حوالي نصف ال160000 طالب شاهدوا
at least one video each week,
على الأقل فيديو واحد كل أسبوع
and over 20,000 finished all the homework,
وفوق ال20.000 أنهوا كل واجباتهم المنزلية
putting in 50 to 100 hours.
منفذين 50 الى 100 ساعة
They got this statement of accomplishment.
لقد حصلوا على هذا التقرير والانجاز
So what have we learned?
لذلك ما الذي تعلمناه ؟
Well, we tried some old ideas
حسناً ، لقد حاولنا بعض الأفكار القديمة
and some new and put them together,
وبعض الجديدة ووضعناها سوياً
but there are more ideas to try.
ولكن هناك الكثير من الأفكار لتجربتها
Sebastian's teaching another class now.
سيباستيان يقوم بتدريس فصل آخر الآن
I'll do one in the fall.
وسأقوم انا بتدريس آخر في الخريف
Stanford Coursera, Udacity, MITx
ستانفورد كورسيرا ، يوداسيتي ، ميتكس
and others have more classes coming.
والآخرون لديهم فصولاً أخرى قادمة.
It's a really exciting time.
إنه لوقت مثير بالفعل
But to me, the most exciting
ولكن بالنسبة لي فإن الجزء
part of it is the data that we're gathering.
الأكثر إثارة فيه هو البيانات التي نجمعها
We're gathering thousands
نحن نقوم بجمع الألاف
of interactions per student per class,
من التفاعلات لكل طالب في كل فصل
billions of interactions altogether,
البلايين من التفاعلات معاً
and now we can start analyzing that,
والآن نستطيع البدء في تحليلها
and when we learn from that,
وعندما نتعلم من ذلك
do experimentations,
نقوم بعمل التجارب
that's when the real revolution will come.
التي تخبرنا متى ستأتي الثورة الحقيقية
And you'll be able to see the results from
وحينها ستستطيعون رؤية النتائج من
a new generation of amazing students.
جيل جديد من الطلاب المدهشين
(Applause)
(تصفيق)